What was that you wanted a you
wanted a high protein zero sugar
ice cream? We can do that come with [Music] me.
So many people asked me to do protein ice cream,
it's one of those things that I couldn't
do before because I was making recipes,
protein based recipes, for a UK business.
They distribute into the UK and Europe
but they don't sell in North America.
I can now tell you how to make good
quality protein ice cream. So none of
these are affiliated, these products.
We're just going to talk quickly about the weight
of the protein ice cream you can buy
in the stores, this is a unopened tub
of Ben & Jerry's which weighs 423g and
an unopened tub of Halo weighs 269g.
Okay that means what you're getting
is mostly air in a Halo ice cream,
you're getting 40% less ice cream because
it's pumped full of air. It uses Erythritol
which is crap and that's likely why they are
stabilizing with tara and guar gum and just
packing it with air because the texture is [__].
All right so to make a high quality protein ice
cream you need to approach it slightly
differently. We're not only going to make
a high quality protein ice cream, we're going to
make a basically zero sugar protein ice cream,
we're going to use xylitol which
is dangerous for dogs so if you
have a if you have a pup, please be careful.
In this pan we have our milk and our cream which
is 250g of 33% cream, 600g of 2% milk and into
this we've put 115g of xylitol and we have put
1.5g of guar gum in there as well. Stirred that up
and popped that in. I did do it on camera but the
camera didn't film it so this is where we are, and
in this container we have our skim milk powder so
there's 50g of skim milk powder, 60g of protein
powder, this is just the protein powder I have,
it's chocolate. Chocolate cake to be specific but
it doesn't really matter which protein powder use.
Some plant-based protein powders don't
dissolve as well as the dairy or whey
based ones so you might get a kind of grainy
texture but you can't do anything about it,
that's just the way some plant-based
proteins are. And on the top we have
our 15g of high quality cocoa all right,
don't use cheap cocoa it tastes like crap,
it sometimes doesn't dissolve properly too.
You want something to make this taste good,
you don't want this to taste like Hershey's,
unless you love Hershey's of course then use
Hershey's cocoa powder. So with our xylitol, our
guar gum, our cream and our milk in there we're
going to stir this up and that is it everything
you need for a high quality protein ice cream.
Let's get it on the hob ,so really nice and
simple, we're just going to get everything
mixed up on the hob we don't need to go
up to 85°C/ 185°F because we are using a
cold processed stabilizer, that's guar gum,
so we're just going to warm this up enough
so that the xylitol is completely dissolved,
the cocoa powder is completely dissolved and
the milk powder and protein powder have also been
completely blended in to make a homogeneous mix.
So when it's completely mixed up just like that,
lovely smooth mixture, we're about 40 to 50°C
here which is this in 104-122°F Fahrenheit we can
actually just take it off the hob, i'm just going
to stir this for a couple of minutes now it's off
the hob. Unfortunately when I started this video
the camera decided not to record so I'm having
to go over a few things again so just to note the
ingredients for this are: 600g of 2% milk, 250g of
33% cream, 115g of xylitol, 60g of protein powder,
50g of skim milk powder, 15g of cocoa and 1.5g of
guar gum. Okay the overrun on these high protein
no sugar ice creams is a very standard but really
irritating commercial process that they do to mask
the bad quality of their ice cream. When you pump
an ice cream full of air, you're reducing the Ice
Crystal size relative to the air pocket size and
there's a level of overrun that creates the best
texture ice cream somewhere in the 25 to 40% range
okay. In that range 25% overrun to 40% overrun,
you get ice cream with ultra high quality
texture the moment you go over that you start
to produce something that is so light that
it no longer starts to taste like ice cream,
it becomes a frozen dessert and fortunately
in different parts of the world there is a law
relating to the amount of overrun that you can
have on ice cream. In the US I think it's 100%
which is stupid high you know legally you can make
ice cream with 100% overrun and still call it ice
cream I don't know what that is but that's when
you go to you know your supermarket and you buy
the absolute junk in 2, 3 or 4 liter containers
for about about five bucks that's what you get,
same in the UK you know you you go and buy really
cheap ice cream you're getting mostly air and it's
just the case of the machines, the batch freezers
or the continuous freezing process machines,
pumping it full of air as it's churning and
increasing the overrun. So if you imagine a
1L base with 40% overrun gives you 1.4L of
final product ,1L of base 100% overrun 2L,
so commercially it goes a lot further it's a
cost-saving exercise and Ben and Jerry's showed
they were prepared to do that as well with their
Sundae range. The Sundae range, I did some reviews
for the Sundae ice creams, the top of those ice
creams had what they called..... what do they
call it? I don't know it was basically ice cream
so their standard base with huge amounts of air
and that was that accounted for one third of the
tub so it's a really easy way for them to say "oh
look we'll charge the same amount for much less
ice cream" so that is why we do what we do at home
because we are in control of what we make.
Home ice cream machines will likely only
achieve... most home ice cream machines will
likely only achieve a 15 to 20% overrun the
higher quality home machines like mine
they can achieve, you know kind of 40%
but you've got to have the recipe right.
So with that mixed up we're going to get
this in the fridge get it chilled
down and then we'll get churning.
The next day I took the base out of the fridge,
gave it a nice little stir to make sure everything
is completely homogenized again and then popped
it in my pre-chilled ice cream machine. Had
this one pre-chilling for about 5 minutes
and it churned beautifully as you can see,
good amount of overrun you know, not too high, and
just loaded up into the container. It was a really
nice ice cream with you know 25-30% overun for my
machine you might not get that on yours depending
on what machine you got but after loading up
the tub, I popped in the freezer overnight and
the next day took it out and look.... it's just
straightforward high quality chocolate ice cream,
nice new bowl. Got this one from Japan and scooped
lovely really nice as you can see this texture,
let me go in a bit closer, it's super creamy no
discernable ice crystals in this it's delicious.
High protein ice cream shouldn't it be
as difficult as people make out on the
internet. To make high protein ice
cream, no it isn't that difficult,
the hardest thing that people do is miscalculate,
people miscalculate all their ingredients and
actually this includes some commercial ice creams,
high protein ice creams and I'll show this in
another video, the nutritional breakdown of
some commercial ice creams and how they have it,
they have it wrong to the point where they're
trying to mislead the consumer but before we
ramble on about this that and the other, let's
try some of this..... it's good .....it's not
just good for protein ice cream, it's GOOD ice
cream, has just over 9g of protein per 100g.
Now let's just let's just think about that
for a second, Halo which sells itself,
advertised itself as a high protein
it really isn't because this has 7g
of protein per 180 ML volumetric so we know
how light this whole tub is so in reality
we're we're almost twice the protein
as a marketable high protein ice cream.
Now skim milk powder it's loaded with protein,
protein powders are different they're not all
created equal but by the time you start messing
around with putting even more in you're going
to create a fudge thickness ice cream base that
won't churn. All right so think about how much
you want and how much you want to advertise or
consume if if you're making ice cream at home,
then how much protein do you want out of
your ice cream? that's problem number one,
problem number two we go down the zero sugar
route. We have use xylitol here no sugar so
not only have we created an ultra high protein ice
cream we've also made a zero sugar ice cream and
we've made it with ingredients and a balance that
means it sits in the freezer for days and days
and days and doesn't turn into an ice block.
So super smooth, tastes just like any other
chocolate ice cream obviously if you don't want
to make chocolate versions of this then you need
to kind of rebalance this recipe completely
because cocoa powder you know I used a 20- 22%
fat cocoa powder in here, that has a significant
effect on the recipe if you remove that and you
use a vanilla protein powder, your recipe is
going to be out of balance but it's relatively
easy to adjust it really is so there we go an
ultra high protein zero sugar ice cream that
actually tastes good it's a luxurious product
it weighs the same as a standard ice cream it's
not pumped full of air so you're not getting a
lot everyone's been asking for this here it is
all right I hope you enjoyed this video let me
know if you want more high protein ice cream
and more zero sugar ice creams I'm quite happy
to do combinations as well so tell me what you
want in the comments like And subscribe so that
you don't miss out and I'll see you next [Music]
[Music] time........ actually this is really good!